Register of the Lamar Henderson collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Lamar Henderson collection
1966-1996
1986-1990
2009C51
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Pamphlets, serial issues, bulletins, newsletters, clippings, other printed matter, circulated material, correspondence, and notes relating to drought and famine in Ethiopia, relief and development assistance to Ethiopia, and political conditions and civil war in Ethiopia.
Henderson, Lamar, collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Henderson, after earning a BA in sociology, went to Ethiopia from 1968 through 1971 as a Peace Corps volunteer, where he participated in design and building projects for the engineering section of the Ministry of National Community Development and Social Affairs. He designed and built several public works projects which fostered his interest in design.
After Henderson returned to the United States, he attended design school at the California Institute of the Arts, where he received an MFA in design. Henderson then earned his master's degree in architecture from the Graduate School of Architecture and Urban Planning at UCLA. He taught for ten years in the School of Architecture and Planning at the Catholic University of America.
Inspired by his Peace Corps experience, Henderson remained involved in Ethiopian support and relief groups once he returned to the United States. He was an active member in the Ethiopian Project Research and Assistance Group (EthioPRAG), a group concerned with raising awareness about famine in Ethiopia and supporting scholarly research of possible solutions. He was also a member of the Bay Area Chapter of Friends of Ethiopia, where he actively tried to recruit and connect with other people who had lived in Ethiopia.
Scope and Content of Collection
Pamphlets, serial issues, bulletins, newsletters, clippings, other printed matter, circulated material, correspondence, and notes relating to drought and famine in Ethiopia, relief and development assistance to Ethiopia, and political conditions and civil war in Ethiopia.
Ethiopia--History--1974-; Droughts--Ethiopia.; Famines--Ethiopia.; International relief.
- Subject File, 1970-1991
  - Eritrea, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Small group of materials about the territory of Eritrea, focused mainly on relief efforts. Eritrean Relief Committee newsletter and newspaper reproductions make up the bulk of the contents.
  - Ethiopian Project Research and Assistance Group (EthioPRAG), 1985-1991 (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    The Ethiopian Project Research and Assistance Group (EthioPRAG) was an American organization aimed at raising awareness and support for famine victims and improving the quality of life for people in Ethiopia. It took over a previous organization called the Ethiopian Famine Relief Organization of the Greater Bay Area, whose newsletters are included here. EthioPRAG's members consisted of Ethiopians and Americans who wanted to get involved to support Ethiopians. The group wanted to take a more active approach in their aid to Ethiopia, as well as concentrate on scholarly research focused on long-term solutions to drought and famine.
    The folders contain EthioPRAG meeting minutes (mostly from 1987 and 1988), newspaper article reproductions, promotional material for EthioPRAG, and information about various conferences hosted by the organization. Brochures and descriptions of the organization are accompanied by personal notes from Henderson.
  - Friends of Ethiopia, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1: 4-5)
    Friends of Ethiopia was a national organization formed in 1985. One of the main goals of the organization was to connect people in the United States who had lived or worked in Ethiopia so they could stay in contact with each other and keep current on events.
    Materials are related to the Bay Area Chapter of the Friends of Ethiopia, with some promotional materials from the national headquarters. A fairly comprehensive collection of newsletters from 1985 through 1991 was kept, along with World News reports and scholarly publications. Other materials included are newspaper reproductions, personal notes, and correspondence related to the recruitment of members to the organization.
  - Tigre, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Small group of papers related to the Tigre region of Ethiopia and the Relief Society of Tigray (REST). The bulk of the material is related to REST and promotes relief efforts for Ethiopian victims of famine.
  - Visit of Ethiopian Ambassador to the United Nations to Stanford, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1: 7-8)
    On December 17, 1987, the Ethiopian government delegation visited Stanford in order to raise awareness about the threat of famine in Ethiopia. The head of the delegation was Kassa Kebede, Ambassador of Ethiopia to the United Nations in Geneva. Materials include newspaper articles and copies of the schedule and agenda for the visit. Additionally, a copy of Proclamations Issued by the National Shengo of the PDRE at Its First Session is included, which was a gift to the hosts of the visit.
  - Ethiopia, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    Newspaper articles, article reproductions, and handwritten notes discussing the 1984 to 1985 famine in Ethiopia. Also includes an Info Pack from the Congressional Research Service at the Library of Congress.
  - Werner Erhard Foundation, 1988 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    In 1988, Werner Erhard visited Ethiopia and interviewed the president, Mengistu Haile Mariam. A transcript of the audio recording is provided, as well as a list of the people and the organizations they represented that Erhard met during his visit.
  - L.A. Ethiopian Church, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    Blue prints for an Ethiopian church, accompanied by handwritten notes and reproductions of photos and descriptions of churches. Vellum drawings and pencil sketches are also included.
- Printed Matter, 1966-1996
  - Newspapers, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    The Struggle Call and the New Era are newspapers published in Ethiopia and written in Amharic. The Struggle Call was published by the Tigray People's Liberation Front, and the New Era was a national newspaper.
    The Ethiopian Mirror was a monthly periodical published in Los Angeles, California, covering Ethiopian news for those living in America.
  - The Africa File, 1987 December (Box-folder 2: 6)
    Published by Ethiopian Airlines to educate travel agents and travel consultants about Ethiopia and to encourage travel to the area.
  - Livestock Dependent (Pastoralists) Food Supply System Food Supply Prospect, 1986 April (Box-folder 2: 7)
    In an effort to predict famine, the Early Warning and Planning Services Relief and Rehabilitation Commission published a system report of the food supply to identify what food stuffs might be in danger of failing. This issue outlines the food supply prospect of the livestock supply system.
  - Project Proposal for Children's Homes, 1985 July (Box-folder 2: 8)
    Proposal put together by the National Children's Commission and the Relief and Rehabilitation Commission of The Provisional Military Government of Socialist Ethiopia. It details a possible solution to deal with children orphaned because of the 1983 to 1984 famine.
  - Hearings before the Subcommittees on Human Rights and International Organizations, International Economic Policy and Trade, and on Africa of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives, One Hundredth Congress, First Session, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    Transcript of two hearings about human rights in Ethiopia covering what the committees discussed in regards to human rights violations in Ethiopia during 1987 and the preceding years.
  - Improving Village Water Supplies in Ethiopia: A Case Study of the Socio-economic Implications, Hanna Kebede, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    Reproduction published by the United Nation's Economic Commission for Africa.
  - The Draft Constitution of the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia (PDRE), 1986 June (Box-folder 2: 11)
    Two reproduction copies of a 1986 draft constitution of the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia presented for discussion. This constitution eventually created the Communist Ethiopian government in 1987.
  - Problems of Communism, 1990 November-December (Box-folder 2: 12)
    Bimonthly publication that provides an overview of and commentary on events in the Soviet Union, China, and other politically similar states. This issue features an essay by Paul B. Henze titled "Marxist Disaster and Cultural Survival in Ethiopia," which discusses the effect of communism in Ethiopia.
  - Horn of Africa: An Independent Journal, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    Quarterly journal dedicated to the Horn of Africa geographic region. This issue has three featured articles discussing Ethiopia.
  - Horn of Africa: An Independent Journal, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    Features an article critiquing the revolution in Ethiopia.
  - Selamta, 1985 Summer (Box-folder 2: 15)
    In-flight magazine provided by Ethiopian Airlines.
  - "Basic Information on Ethiopia's Long and Medium Term Economic Development Plans as well as Settlement and Villagization Programmes,", 1987 May (Box-folder 2: 16)
    Reproduction of a report produced by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Addis Ababa outlining information about Ethiopia's economic prospects.
  - "Housing in Ethiopia,", 1966 January (Box-folder 2: 17)
    Reproduction of a report on housing in Ethiopia produced by the Department of Housing and Urban Development of the United States. This report was part of a series of reports about housing in developing countries.
  - People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    Printed pamphlet, written in Amharic, from the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia giving a description of self-administration that was presented to the first National Congress in 1987.
  - "African Famine: The Search for Solutions," Congressional Research Service Issue Brief, 1992 February 18 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    Information from relief efforts in 1991 and projections of relief efforts needed for 1992, detailed by region.
  - "Africa: U. S. Foreign Assistance Issues," Congressional Research Service Issue Brief, 1992 February 4 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    Report detailing the amount of aid the United States sent to sub-Saharan African countries for famine, health, and political issues during 1991.
  - "Ethiopia: War and Famine," Congressional Research Service Issue Brief, 1991 August 5 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Report detailing the history of Ethiopia's different political regimes and the effect they had on the relationship between Ethiopia and the United States. The brief starts with United States relations under the rule of emperor Haile Selassie in the post-World War II era and continues through 1991.
  - Ethioscope, 1996 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    Quarterly magazine focused on Ethiopia's foreign and domestic issues. This issue features articles on Ethio-Japanese relations, the Organization of African Unity, and the United Nations.
  - People's Voice, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    Quarterly magazine published by the Foreign Relations Bureau of the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). This issue features articles on the fourteen year history of the TPLF and the formation of the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front.
  - Mender, 1987 May (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Publication promoting villagization and resettlement in Ethiopia by the government and Comrade Mengitsu Haile-Mariam. The efforts were organized through the National Villagization Co-ordinating Committee.
  - "Eritrea in the Western Media,", 1988 January-June (Box-folder 3: 5)
    Compilation of newspaper clippings about Eritrea and Ethiopian issues affecting Eritrea produced in the Western media. Compiled by Concerned Americans and Eritreans of the San Francisco Bay Area to increase understanding of Eritrean issues.
  - "Our Popular Objective Needs, Our Co-Ordinated Effort,", 1987 October 9 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Statement issued by the Council of State of the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia in order to gain support for the new government.
  - Tigray: Ethiopia's Untold Story, 1985 October (Box-folder 3: 7)
    Small book published by the Relief Society of Tigray UK Support Committee to bring attention to the issues facing the small province between 1983 and 1985. Ethiopian conflicts and drought affected the Tigray region on an equal or larger scale than the rest of the country, but it was not as covered in Western media.
  - Combatting the Effects of Cyclical Drought in Ethiopia, 1985 January (Box-folder 3: 8)
    Short book published by the Ethiopian Relief and Rehabilitation Commission describing the drought situation in Ethiopia from 1970 through 1990. The book outlines the history of drought in the region, efforts to combat drought, and prospects for preventing drought-related famine in the future.
  - People's Democratic Programme of the Tigray People's Liberation Front, 1983 May (Box-folder 3: 9)
    Small pamphlet describing the history of Tigray and outlining the objectives and organization of the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The program was adopted by the Second Organizational Congress in 1983.
  - Enriching the Constitution, 1986 August (Box-folder 3: 10)
    Small pamphlet describing the process of approving the draft constitution of the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia throughout the 1980s.
  - Tigray Document to the 39th Session of the United Nations General Assembly, 1984 September (Box-folder 3: 11)
    Pamphlet prepared by the Tigray People's Liberation Front to be presented to the United Nations General Assembly. The pamphlet gives a brief background on the history of the conflict between Tigray and Ethiopia, and it formally presents appeals to the United Nations to create a united front against the Ethiopian regime.
  - Hearing before the Subcommittees on Human Rights and International Organizations and on Africa of the Committee of Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives, One Hundredth Congress, Second Session, 1988 April 21 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    Transcript of the hearings updating the Committee of Foreign Affairs on the famine in Ethiopia.
  - Ensuring the Rights of Nationalities, 1987 September (Box-folder 3: 13)
    Issued by the preparatory committee for the founding of the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia, this pamphlet was a promotional description of the way the new government was going to improve the lives of Ethiopians.
  - Mengistu Haile Mariam Replies to Questions from "Time" Magazine, 1986 July (Box-folder 3: 14)
    Pamphlet containing the transcript of an interview of Mengistu Haile Mariam by Time magazine. The interview was conducted in July 1986 before the People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia was officially established. Excerpts from this interview were published in the August 4, 1986 issue of Time.
  - Facts of Eritrea, 1988 October (Box-folder 3: 15)
    Booklet created by the Eritrean Professionals Action Committee containing general information and history about the country of Eritrea.
  - Ethiopia: A Guide to Investments, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    Booklet giving an overview of Ethiopia's economy and describing policy changes that affect foreign, domestic, and joint investments.
  - Beyond the Famine: An Examination of the Issues behind Famine in Ethiopia, 1988 January (Box-folder 3: 17)
    Food for the Hungry International (FHI) compiled five research papers whose topics addressed issues related to the famine in Ethiopia. The papers were reviewed by subject specialists and cover topics such as the Ethiopian economy, survival strategies, and agriculture.
  - Background Notes: Ethiopia, 1985 August (Box-folder 3: 18)
    Background Notes is a series of pamphlets produced by the United States Department of State about various countries. This issue on Ethiopia gives a description of Ethiopia's economy, government, history, and travel information.
  - Rural Water Supply, Operation and Maintenance Training Program, 1982 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    Report prepared for the government of Ethiopia by the International Labour Organisation of the United Nations Development Programme on rural water supplies. A training program was implemented in order to prepare the Ethiopian water company's employees for new wells that would be drilled to supply more water to the region's inhabitants. This report evaluates the training programs and offers recommendations for improvement.
  - Book on traditional Ethiopian cooking, 1988 (Box-folder 3: 20)